A Guide to the Steele and Johnson Manufacturing Company Records 1980.0040
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Steele and Johnson Manufacturing Company Records
undated, 1837-1937
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1980.0040
195 Linear Feet
The Steele and Johnson Manufacturing Company was established as the Waterbury Jewell Company in 1851 and soon changed its name to the Steele and Johnson Button Company. In 1865 the company established its New York store, and in 1875 this manufacturer of brass buttons and various metal goods changed its name to the Steele and Johnson Manufacturing Company. Steele and Johnson produced and sold items primarily to brass companies and other businesses in Connecticut and Massachusetts, with customers in New York, Pennsylvania, Kentucky, Ohio, Illinois, Michigan, and California. During World War I it produced goods for the army and the government.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
The Steele and Johnson Manufacturing Company records were donated to the University Libraries by Yale University in January 1980.
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence (1866-1937) consists of four subseries: Incoming, Letters from Connecticut and New York Store, Outgoing, and Outgoing: Store. Incoming Correspondence consists mainly of credit reports, complaints, and information about the company's financial difficulties and dissolution. Outgoing Correspondence includes information about a 1905 industrial accident at the company. The incoming correspondence constitutes the bulk of the entire collection. It was heavily concentrated for a short time period. Since most of this correspondence was routine orders and inquiries, the Archives staff conducted a sampling process, which preserves representative examples of the files. The series is arranged chronologically.
Series II: Administrative Records (undated, 1837-1909) contains such items as stock data, federal reserve charts, address books, contracts, creditor and bankruptcy reports, employee data, insurance information, summonses, and tax data. This series is arranged alphabetically.
Series III: General Accounting (1903-1933) includes ledgers, journals, and check registers, as well as volumes of expense analysis, cash journals, and general ledgers. This series is arranged chronologically.
Series IV: Labor (undated, 1882-1922) contains payroll sheets, salary information, and employee data. Three are also several volumes of payroll analysis and contract labor records.
Series V: Production (1874-1879, 1930) consists of inventory and stock on hand ledgers as well as analyses of supplies ledgers.
Series VI: Sales (undated, 1865, 1884-1885) consists of volumes of sales data, as well as price quotations, salesmen's reports, price lists, and orders. With the exception of the final items in the listing, Hitchcock & Castle oversized sales ledger sheets, the materials in the series are arranged alphabetically.
History
The Steele and Johnson Manufacturing Company, one of many companies that composed Connecticut's thriving brass industry in the 19th century, was established as the Waterbury Jewell Company in 1851 and soon changed its name to the Steele and Johnson Button Company. In 1865 the company established its New York store, and in 1875 this manufacturer of brass buttons and various metal goods changed its name to the Steele and Johnson Manufacturing Company. Steele and Johnson produced and sold items primarily to brass companies and other businesses in Connecticut and Massachusetts, with customers in New York, Pennsylvania, Kentucky, Ohio, Illinois, Michigan, and California. During World War I it produced goods for the army and the government.
Although two-thirds of the nation's brass was produced in and around Waterbury by 1926, the company ceased its business operations in 1933, when it employed between five hundred and six hundred employees. In 1941 the capital stock of Steele and Johnson was purchased by the Waterbury Button Company.
Custodial History
The records were originally transferred from the company to Yale University in 1941.
Scope and Content
The records in this collection document the business proceedings of the Steele and Johnson Manufacturing Company from 1865 to about 1937, with the bulk dating between 1874 and 1930. The types of materials include correspondence, inventories, business directories, and financial records. There are no materials documenting the founding and early years of the company. The materials are arranged in six series.
The collection is incomplete and there are many gaps. The records were originally transferred from the company to Yale University in 1941. These records did not include the original minute meeting book, which is presumed lost.
Correspondence; Inventories; Directories; Connecticut (state); Financial Records; Brass industry and trade
- Series I: Correspondence, 1866-1937
  - Subseries A: Incoming Correspondence, 1874-1937
    - 1874-1877 (Box 1)
    - 1877-1882 (Box 2)
    - 1882-1884 (Box 3)
    - 1884-1886 (Box 4)
    - 1886 (Box 5)
    - 1886-1887 (Box 6)
    - 1887 (Box 7-8)
    - 1887-1888 (Box 9)
    - 1888 (Box 10)
    - 1888-1889 (Box 11)
    - 1889 (Box 12-14)
    - 1889-1890 (Box 15)
    - 1890 (Box 16-17)
    - 1890-1891 (Box 18)
    - 1891 (Box 19-22)
    - 1891-1892 (Box 23)
    - 1892 (Box 24)
    - 1892-1893 (Box 25)
    - 1893 (Box 26)
    - 1893-1894 (Box 27)
    - 1894-1895 (Box 28)
    - 1895 (Box 29)
    - 1895 (Box 30)
    - 1896, 1900, 1905 (Box 31)
    - 1905 (Box 32)
    - 1905-1906 (Box 33)
    - 1906 (Box 34-35)
    - 1906, 1910 (Box 36)
    - 1915-1937 (Box 37)
  - Subseries B: Letters from Connecticut and New York Store, 1876-1906
    - 1876-1882 (Box 38)
    - 1883-1885 (Box 39)
    - 1890, 1892 (Box 40)
    - 1892 (Box 41)
    - 1892-1893 (Box 42)
    - 1893-1894 (Box 43)
    - 1894, 1905-1906 (Box 44)
    - 1906 (Box 45)
  - Subseries C: Outgoing Correspondence, 1866-1931
    - 1866-1876 (Box 46)
    - 1875-1878 (Box 47)
    - 1878-1882 (Box 48)
    - 1882-1884 (Box 49)
    - 1883-1886 (Box 50)
    - 1885-1887 (Box 51)
    - 1886-1888 (Box 52)
    - 1887-1888 (Box 53)
    - 1888-1889 (Box 54)
    - 1889-1890 (Box 55)
    - 1890 (Box 56)
    - 1890-1891 (Box 57)
    - 1891 (Box 58-59)
    - 1891-1894 (Box 60)
    - 1893 (Box 61)
    - 1893-1894 (Box 62)
    - 1894 (Box 63)
    - 1894-1895 (Box 64)
    - 1897-1904 (Box 65)
    - 1904-1905 (Box 66)
    - 1905-1906 (Box 67)
    - 1906-1907 (Box 68)
    - 1907 (Box 69)
    - 1907-1908 (Box 70)
    - 1908-1909 (Box 71)
    - 1909 (Box 72)
    - 1910-1911 (Box 73)
    - 1911-1912 (Box 74)
    - 1912 (Box 75-76)
    - 1912-1913 (Box 77)
    - 1913 (Box 78-80)
    - 1913-1914 (Box 81)
    - 1914 (Box 82-83)
    - 1914-1915 (Box 84)
    - 1915 (Box 85-86)
    - 1916 (Box 87-89)
    - 1917 (Box 90-92)
    - 1918 (Box 93-95)
    - 1919 (Box 96-98)
    - 1920 (Box 99-102)
    - 1921 (Box 103-105)
    - 1922 (Box 106-108)
    - 1923 (Box 109-112)
    - 1924 (Box 113)
    - 1925 (Box 114)
    - 1924 (Box 115)
    - 1925 (Box 116-118)
    - 1929 (Box 119-121)
    - 1930 (Box 122-124)
    - 1931 (Box 125-127)
  - Subseries D: Outgoing Correspondence: Store, 1889-1930
    - 1889-1892 (Box 128)
    - 1899-1907 (Box 129)
    - 1911-1913 (Box 130)
    - 1913-1914 (Box 131)
    - 1914-1916 (Box 132)
    - 1917-1920 (Box 133)
    - 1921-1923 (Box 134)
    - 1924-1925 (Box 135)
    - 1929 (Box 136)
    - 1930 (Box 137)
- Series II: Administrative Records, undated, 1837-1909
  - Address books, undated (Box 138)
  - Account data, 1858-1916 (Box 139)
  - Accounting, 1933; (2 folders)
  - Accounts paid, undated
  - Audit of treasurer's books, 1898-1900
  - Beecher & Peck, 1888-1889
  - Benedict & Burnham: statements, 1881-1882
  - Bureau of Labor Statistics reports, undated
  - Buttons: orders/contracts for, 1898-1909
  - Census, 1900, 1904-1905
  - James B. Clow & Son, 1904-1909
  - Correspondence: orders/shipments, undated
  - Contracts, 1880-1900
  - Contracts, c. 1900; (2 folders)
  - Economics Course materials, 1948 (Box 140)
  - Employee data, undated
  - Equipment specifications, undated
  - Estimates, undated; (4 folders)
  - Evertsen, H.E.: sales agent, undated
  - Federal Reserve charts, undated
  - Insurance appraisal, undated
  - Insurance companies: financial statements, undated
  - Insurance data, undated
  - Insurance policies, undated; (8 folders) (Box 141)
  - Insurance record, undated
  - Insurance reports, undated; (2 folders)
  - Inventory sheets, 1900-1905
  - Invoices, undated; (2 folders)
  - License agreement, undated
  - Log (unidentified), undated
  - Manufacturer's Gazette of gas and electric fixtures, undated
  - Mustomatik Specialities, Inc., undated; (3 folders)
  - Nevins Townsend letter book, 1837-1878
  - New York store: expenses, undated
  - New York store: statements, undated
  - Order data, undated
  - Orders, 1898-1901
  - Orders, 1898-1935; (4 folders)
  - Pamphlets, undated (Box 142)
  - Patent papers, 1886-1888
  - Payroll reports, 1927
  - Product information, undated
  - Royal Arcanum Bulletin, 1919-1924; (2 folders)
  - Salary ledger, undated
  - Salary ledger: Uniform Button Association, 1899-1905
  - Sales/stocks on hand: Benedict & Burnham, undated; (2 folders)
  - Stockholder dividend notifications, undated
  - Summons, undated
  - Suppliers, undated
  - Tax forms/assessments, undated
  - The Guide, 1919-1924; (2 folders)
  - Tooling authorizations, undated
  - U.S. Ordinance Department, 1918-1919
  - Waterbury Building & Loan, Assoc., undated; (2 folders)
  - Estimates, undated; (2 vols.) (Box 143)
  - Ansonia Manufacturing Co., 1901-1910 (Box 144)
  - Ansonia Manufacturing Co., 1910; (1 vol.)
  - Metal Trades Directories, 1887-1891; (3 vols.) (Box 145)
  - "Money Market Essays": Federal Reserve Bank, 1952 Mar
  - "Federal Reserve Charts on Bank Credit, Money Rates and Business": Board of Governors of Federal Reserve System, 1951 Apr
  - "Commodity Markets and the Public Interest" Chicago Board of Trade, 1953 Sep, 1956
  - Waterbury & Naugatuck Directories, 1898, 1901-1902; (3 vols.)
  - Waterbury & Naugatuck Directories, undated; (10 vols.) (Box 146)
  - Business Tax Guide, undated
  - Equipment ledgers, undated; (3 folders) (Box 147)
  - Tooling ledger, undated
  - Property inventory, undated
- Series III: General Accounting, 1903-1933
  - Private ledgers, 1904-1911 (Box 148)
  - Journal, 1915-1924; (4 vols.) (Box 149)
  - Unidentified records, 1903
  - Payments made: special accounts, 1908, 1913-1914
  - Check register, 1915-1933; (4 vols.) (Box 150)
  - Uncollectible accounts, 1910-1932; (1 vol.)
    - Volumes
      - Expense analysis, undated; (5 vols.)
      - Expense Journal, 1903-1912
      - Cash Plus Journal, undated
      - Suspense ledger, undated
      - General ledger, c. 1914
- Series IV: Labor, undated, 1882-1922
  - Employee forms, undated (Box 151)
  - Employee cards, undated; (4 envelopes)
  - Employee certificates, undated; (4 envelopes)
  - Employee records, undated
  - Income tax cards/data, undated; (5 folders)
  - Income tax cards/data, undated (Box 152)
  - Trial balance ledgers, 1900-1903; (3 folders) (Box 153)
  - Time book ledger, 1882-1883
  - Analyses of non-productive labor ledger, 1916-1922
  - Ledger (unidentified), 1886-1897
  - Pay Rate ledger, undated (Box 154)
  - Pay Rate ledger, undated (Box 155)
    - Volumes
      - Payroll analysis, undated; (5 vols.)
      - Contractor's labor, undated
- Series V: Production, undated, 1874-1890, 1930
  - Analysis of supplies, undated (Box 156)
  - Inventory, undated
  - Shipping room inventory, 1930 Jun 27-28 (Box 157)
  - Stock on hand: Waterbury and New York, 1874-1875, 1878-1879
- Series VI: Sales, undated, 1865, 1884-1885
  - Contracts, undated; (2 folders) (Box 158)
  - Ledger index, undated
  - Ledgers, undated; (4 folders)
  - Price lists, undated
  - Price quote ledger, undated
  - Sales ledger, undated
  - Sales ledger sheet, 1874-1875
  - Sales ledger book, undated
  - Salesmen's reports, undated; (5 folders) (Box 159)
  - Store orders, undated; (6 folders)
  - Sales by Hitchcock & Castle: ledger, undated; (3 folders) (Box 160)
    - Volumes
      - Sales ledger, undated; (5 vols.)
      - Sales record, undated; (2 vols.)
      - Sales journal, undated; (13 vols.)